Madam Chen!
陈大娘子
You are late.
你来晚了
You must drink a penalty drink later.
一会儿要罚酒一杯
Madam Chen.
陈大娘子
Madam Liu!
刘夫人
Look at Madam Song's outfit today.
快看看 今天宋夫人这打扮
She's looking more and more noble.
可是越来越有贵气了
I'm flattered, Madam Liu.
刘夫人 您过奖了
It is my honor to be invited
今天能够得到各位夫人的邀请
by you ladies today.
那才是我的荣幸呢
It's an imperial green jade bracelet!
帝王绿的翡翠玉镯
This is truly hard to come by.
这可真真的不好找啊
Look at the transparency
看这水头
and the color.
这色泽
It must be worth a lot.
价值不菲吧
Let's talk while we walk.
边走边说
Let's go.
走走走
This bracelet is
这镯子呀
a greeting gift from the Magistrate's wife.
就是县令夫人送的见面礼罢了
No wonder! So it was a gift from your in-law.
怪不得 是亲家母送的呀
Yes.
是呀
-Oh, my. -My apologies.
哎呀 失礼了
You wretched girl!
你这个臭丫头
You... Why are you here?
你 你怎么在这儿
You didn't follow me here just to cause trouble, did you?
你不是故意跟着我过来捣乱的吧
What? Did you buy this building?
怎么 这楼你买下来了
If you can come, why can't I?
你能来我不能来
Do you know each other?
你们认识啊
No. Who would know her?
不认识 谁认识她呀
Madam Liu, let me tell you something.
刘夫人 我跟你说
My son's marriage was
我儿这婚事
entirely arranged by the Magistrate.
全凭县尊安排
The Magistrate is from a scholarly family.
人家县尊大人是书香门第
-Come often if you like it. -He values
好吃您就多来 看重的是
character and upbringing.
人品修养
The betrothal gifts followed ancient customs.
这聘礼啊走了个古法
But my daughter-in-law brought a generous dowry.
倒是儿媳妇陪嫁丰厚
Marriage is
这姻缘哪
all about matching social status.
讲究的就是门当户对
If the character and upbringing are poor,
这人品修养不行的呀
such a marriage
这婚事啊
-shall never take place. -Indeed.
可万万结不得
Right?
是吧
The Magistrate is truly generous.
这县太爷可真是大方
Congratulations
恭喜了
on selling your Scholar Song for a good price.
把你家宋举人卖了个好价钱
You...
你
Well...
这
Wretched girl!
臭丫头
Let's go inside quickly.
咱们赶紧进去吧
Don't let such a vulgar person
不要让这等粗鄙之人
ruin our mood.
扰了咱们的兴致
Right? Come on in.
对吧 来来来
What is she talking about?
她说的是
Just nonsense. Forget about it.
胡说八道的 什么呀
Here's a toast to you both.
浅浅敬二位一杯
Manager Yu, you are very experienced
俞掌柜迎来送往
in receiving guests.
很是老道
It seems you have indeed met a lot of people.
看来确实认识不少人
Our restaurant welcomes guests from everywhere.
小店八方来客
We believe harmony brings wealth.
讲究和气生财
In business,
做生意嘛
it's always good to know more people.
多认识些人总归是好的
Please make yourselves at home, sirs.
那二位贵客请自便
I need to go attend to other guests now.
我先去招呼其他的客人了
Manager, what's wrong?
掌柜的 怎么了
You look pale.
脸色都变了
The man in there just touched me.
刚刚那里面的人摸了我一下
I don't know why, but that single touch
不知为何 就碰了那么一下
gave me the creeps.
我全身毛骨悚然的
Another guest who tried to grope you?
又是想揩油的客人
How shameless.
真是臭不要脸
It's not really about groping.
也不是揩油不揩油
I feel like I've seen him somewhere before.
总感觉在哪儿见过
Who was that young lady we met at the door just now?
方才门口那个小娘子是谁呀
She is called Fan Changyu.
她呀 叫樊长玉
She's a famous disaster from my hometown, Xigu Lane.
是我们以前西固巷有名的灾祸
The fortune tellers all say
这算命的都说了
she is a rare jinx seen only once in a millennium.
她可是千年难遇的天煞孤星
She not only caused her parents' deaths,
不仅克死了她爹她娘
but her uncle was also killed because of her.
连她的大伯都被她害死了
It even went to court!
还闹上了公堂呢
By the way,
对了
just in the middle of this month,
就这个月中啊
a group of bandits broke into her home at night,
她家半夜进了一伙山匪
having killed so many people!
杀死了好多人
Everyone in Lin'an knows about this.
这事闹得整个林安都知道
I wonder
她这双手
how many people have touched her hands
不知道被多少人碰过
for her to stay so composed
才练就了如今她这般泰然自若
and feel no shame at all.
全无矜持
I've searched everywhere all these years, yet I failed to find her.
孤这些年到处寻她不着
I didn't expect her to be doing so well in Lin'an,
没想到她竟在林安混得风生水起
and to have met so many men.
还结识了那么多男人
Perhaps it's just her business dealings.
或许只是生意上的往来呢
You are still making excuses for her.
你还在替她解释
I dare not.
属下不敢
Back then, she left false clues about her fleeing beyond the pass,
当年她留下逃往关外的假线索
causing me to search for her in vain for 6 years.
害得孤白白找了她六年
Never thought she'd establish herself in just 6 years
没想到短短六年就站稳脚跟
and open such a large restaurant.
开了这么大的酒楼
This woman is really something.
这个女人不简单啊
Understood.
明白
I will go investigate her connections immediately.
属下这就去查查她身边的人脉
Also, investigate the men around her.
同时查一下她周遭的男人
For anyone who has touched her,
凡是碰过她的
chop off the parts they touched her with,
何处碰触 便剁何处
and present them to me.
献于孤面前
Yes.
是
I will give the orders right away.
属下这就吩咐下去
Why would Manager Yu hire someone like that?
俞掌柜为何要请这种人做事
In the restaurant business,
做酒楼买卖
nothing's worse than bad luck.
最怕晦气了
Perhaps Manager Yu
兴许这俞掌柜啊
doesn't know this girl's background,
不知道这个丫头的底细
so she let a jinx in.
这才招了灾星入门
Madams.
各位夫人
Manager Yu.
俞掌柜
What "jinx"?
什么灾星进门啊
We don't have such a dish at Yixiang Restaurant.
我们溢香楼可没这道菜
Manager Yu,
俞掌柜
we are only looking out for your best interests.
我们可都是一心为了你好
This jinx
这灾星啊
can bring death to people.
会克死人的
Really?
真的啊
But I heard
可我怎么听说
that she supported a scholar fiancé for years.
她养了个读书人未婚夫很多年
Once the scholar passed the provincial exam,
人家考上了个举人
he betrayed her and broke off the engagement.
就过河拆桥的把婚退了
In my point of view,
要我说啊
the mother and son are the real ingrates
那对母子才是白眼狼
and jinxes.
大灾星
They not only harmed the young girl
不仅害人家小姑娘
but also her parents.
更坑害人家爹娘
So this talk of a jinx
那这灾星之说
might just be a false rumor.
或许是以讹传讹吧
You're right, Madam Liu.
刘夫人说得是
Mrs. Fan
这樊娘子啊
not only takes care of her sister all by herself.
一个人照顾妹妹不说
Since she joined our Yixiang Restaurant,
自从她来了我们溢香楼
my braised meat business
我这卤肉生意啊
has been booming.
真是越来越好
I think
要我说呀
she's actually an auspicious blessing!
她是个福星
However, Madam Song,
不过宋夫人
who told you she was a jinx?
你是听谁说她是个灾星啊
Just some gossip, I suppose.
也就是人传人的话吧
Why do women
这女人啊
have to make things hard for other women?
何苦为难女人
Spouting nonsense and gossiping all day
整日胡说八道 乱嚼舌根
will bring about God's punishment.
是会遭天谴的
As educated and reasonable as you are, Madam Song,
宋夫人知书达理
how could you gossip like some filthy trash?
怎会和腌臜货一般嚼人口舌
You must have been deceived.
定是让人蒙蔽了双眼
Why are there still some dishes not served?
这菜怎么还没上齐
I'll go check on them.
我去催催
Madams, please enjoy the food.
各位夫人请慢用
Okay.
好
You know what?
不知道吧
This manager
这个掌柜的
got pregnant out of wedlock.
也是个未婚先孕的主
Who knows whose bastard
这肚子里啊
she carried in her belly?
还不知道怀的谁的野种呢
"Why do women have to make things hard for other women?" Ridiculous.
什么女人何苦为难女人
I think she's obviously
我看她分明就是
an immoral slut
跟樊长玉一路
just like Fan Changyu.
不守妇道的贱货
Let's
咱们呢
not let other people's gossip
莫让他人的是非
ruin our mood.
搅了咱们姐妹的雅兴
Yes, exactly.
是呀
Let's get back to the point.
我们言归正传
A bunch of noisy gossips.
一群聒噪的长舌妇
According to them,
照她们的说法
the child might be hiding in this restaurant.
这孩子说不定就藏在酒楼里面
The one who talks the most,
话最多的那个
teach her a lesson.
让她长长记性
Understood.
是
-Madam Liu. -Do you think I'm drunk?
刘夫人
You drank too much.
喝多了
For this matter, please put in a good word for me
这事我就麻烦你在亲家公面前
-in front of your son's father-in-law. -Don't worry. Just leave it to me.
美言几句
"Bring about God's punishment"?
说什么遭天谴
I think the one to suffer God's punishment
我看真遭天谴
s-should be that wretched girl!
也 也应该是那个臭丫头才对
If God
这老天爷呀
really sees us all,
真要是有眼的话
He should make that wretched girl...
就应该把那个臭丫头
You'd better think twice before you speak nonsense
乱说话之前掂量一下
and watch your mouth.
管好自己的臭嘴
If you spout nonsense again,
再胡言乱语
it won't end as easily as today.
就不像今天这么简单了
O-Okay.
好 好好
I-I get it.
知 知 知道了
Madam.
夫人
Are there any pig ears left?
猪耳朵还有吗
None left today.
今日没了
You may come again tomorrow.
你们明日再来吧
It's almost New Year.
这马上就要过年了
Our braised meat is
咱们卤肉啊
selling better and better.
卖得也是越来越好
You've worked really hard.
你真是辛苦了
You're the one working hard,
你才辛苦了
busy with so many things every day.
每日忙这么多事
Making money is never easy.
这挣钱哪有容易的
However,
不过
although our braised meat is selling well,
咱们卤肉卖得虽然还不错
if we want to take it to the next level,
但未来还想更上一层楼
we could design an emblem for our braised meat.
可以为自己的卤肉设计一个图徽
An emblem?
图徽
But my braised meat is either sliced and served on a plate,
可我家的卤肉不是切好装盘上桌
or wrapped in oil paper for takeout.
就是用油纸包好外带走
What's the use of an emblem?
用图徽干啥使
It's exceptionally useful.
大有用的
Come out here.
你出来
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
你瞧瞧
at these shops downstairs from mine.
我楼下这几家铺子
Fang's tea,
方家的茶叶
Li's wine.
李家的酒水
[Luo's Pawnshop]
是不是每一家都有图徽
And each one is unique.
而且各家图徽都不一样
You can tell whose shop it is at a glance.
一看便知谁是谁家的铺子
Later, think of a design for your emblem.
回头啊你想好图徽的样式
You can make a banner to hang by the signboard,
可以做个布幅挂在招牌旁
so people can see it from afar.
让人远远就能瞧见
And make some more oil paper.
再做一些油纸
Print the emblem on the oil paper, too.
油纸上面也要印上图徽
When someone buys braised meat,
有人来买卤肉
wrap it in that oil paper.
你就用油纸包
Your fame will surely surpass the Wang's.
这名气不愁大不过那个王记去
I got it.
好
I'll find you
我呢给你找一个
a scholar with nice handwriting.
字写得还不错的秀才
Let's get this done today.
咱今日就把这事给办了
Qianqian.
浅姐
My husband can write as well.
我夫婿他也会写字
I'll just ask him to help.
我找他就行
How is your husband's handwriting?
你夫婿字写得怎么样
Excellent.
特别好
Really.
真的
Even more beautiful than his face.
比他脸还好看
That impressive?
这么厉害
Then he must be as great as the legendary calligraphers,
那岂不是王羲之
Wang Xizhi and Zhong Yao!
钟繇再世
Wang Xi...
王羲
I don't know who those two are,
我虽不知道你说的这两人是谁
but I think he's about that good.
但我觉得应该差不多吧
Changyu,
长玉妹子
I really love
你这性格呀
your personality.
我可太喜欢了
Sir, your handwriting is truly elegant.
公子的字写得真俊秀啊
-Yes. -Having worked here for years,
是啊 我老李这店里这么多年
I've never seen anyone's handwriting
还从未见过谁的字
as good as yours, sir.
写得像公子这般好啊
Truly amazing.
真是了不得
-It's so well written. -Manager, look.
写得真好 掌柜的 您看
It's so beautiful.
写得真好看
Do you want to take a break?
要不要休息会儿
No need. I'll keep writing.
不用 我继续写
Changyu.
长玉
Your husband's handwriting...
你夫婿这字
It's really good!
写得真好
Much better than that Wang...
比那个王
Wang something.
王什么的写得好多了
Fine. Beauty is in the eye of the beholder.
好 情人眼里出西施
Of course it's good.
哪能不好
Yes. No matter what Zheng writes or draws,
对 只要是姐夫写的画的
I think it's the best.
宁娘都觉得好
Fuling, take Changning upstairs to have some goodies.
茯苓 带宁娘上去吃点东西
You can eat whatever you want.
想吃什么就吃什么
Thank you, Fairy Sister.
谢谢仙女姐姐
That's so sweet.
嘴真甜
Off you go.
去吧
Changyu,
长玉
you really found yourself
你还真是找了个
a husband good with both brains and brawn.
能文能武的好夫婿啊
Thank you for the compliment.
多谢夸奖
No need to thank me.
谢什么
From today on,
从今天起啊
we must stick together.
咱们一定要同出一口气
Show those gossips
让那些碎嘴子们瞧瞧
that we young women are also capable of great deeds!
咱们小娘子也能成大业
-I want some, too! -I also want some!
我要 我也要
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
我也要 我要
Qianqian, you're so insightful.
浅姐 你可真厉害
You said drawing these things
你说要画这些东西
would attract a lot of people, and it really did!
果然能吸引这么多人
You're mistaken.
你搞错了
The real attraction is
吸引人的呀
your husband.
是你那夫婿
Why are you still standing there?
你还愣着干吗
Go help him.
快去帮忙啊
Go, go, go.
快去快去快去
I'll help you.
我来帮你
Here you are.
来
Isn't this the meat you wanted?
这不是你要的肉吗
This was just wrapped up.
这个是刚刚包的
Yes.
是
Is what he takes different?
他拿的不一样
Yes, the meat he hands over smells better.
是 他给的肉更香
-I want some, too! -I also want some!
我也要 我也要
Give it to me! Me!
给我 给我
That's mine! Give it to me! I want some, too!
我的 给我 我也要
Here you are.
给
You can do it.
加油 加油 加油
It's fine. It's okay.
没关系 没关系
You weighed this wrong.
你这称得不对
No rush, sir.
别着急 公子
No need to rush.
不用着急
It's underweight.
不足称
I cut an extra piece.
我多切了一块
Here you are.
来
What does it have to do with you?
跟你有什么关系
Stay out of this.
多管闲事
-I want some, too! -I also want some!
我也要 我也要
-Me, too. -Any meat left?
我也要 还有吗
I shouldn't have let you come.
早知道不让你来了
-Give it to me. I'll pay double the price. -I also want some!
这给我 我也要 我给双倍价格
-I want some, too. -Me, too.
我也要 我也要
Is there any left?
还有吗
Sorry, sir.
不好意思
We're sold out for today.
今儿都卖光了
What about those in the back?
后面那些呢
Those are just scraps.
都是碎肉
Scraps are fine, too.
碎肉也行呀
Are you selling them or not?
到底卖不卖
Yes. If you pay, I'll sell.
卖 给钱就卖
Here, take it.
来来来 拿着
Your hands are greasy.
你手上有油
Be careful not to dirty the paper on top.
别把上面的纸弄脏了
This calligraphy is brilliant.
这字不错呀
Using it to wrap meat is
用来包肉
squandering a treasure.
简直是暴殄天物
Really nice.
真不错
"Squandering a treasure"?
暴殄天物
What does that mean?
暴殄天物什么意思
Let's pack up.
收了吧
I'm not drunk.
没喝多
Take care, Mr. Wu.
吴公子慢走
Qianqian.
浅浅
Go wait for me in the carriage.
去马车上等我
Did you enjoy your drink, Mr. Wu?
吴公子喝得可好
It's getting late. It's time to go home.
夜深了 也该归家了
Why go home?
回什么家呀
Everyone knows I am
谁不知道我吴某
a regular here.
是你这儿的常客呀
-Mr. Wu. -Let's go.
吴公子 走
Drink a few more cups with me.
再陪我喝两杯
I'm doing this for your own good.
我也是为公子好
If you go back late,
您这要是回去回晚了
Mrs. Wu will come cause trouble
吴夫人又要找我们
for our Yixiang Restaurant again.
溢香楼的麻烦了
Don't use that fierce woman to pressure me.
你少拿那个母老虎来压我
Listen carefully.
我告诉你
If you don't keep me good company today,
你今儿不给我陪好了
don't expect to keep this place running smoothly.
你这小楼也甭想给我好好开下去
Mr. Wu, please mind your manners.
吴公子 请你自重些
Go away!
去
How dare you, a maid, talk to me like that?
你一个婢女敢跟我这么搭话
-Who taught you to do that? -Mr. Wu!
谁教你那么做事的 吴公子
Mr. Wu.
吴公子
Calm down, please.
消消气
I'll drink with you.
我陪您喝
Bring the cups.
拿杯子来
Cheers.
喝
How dare you,
像你这种无赖
a scoundrel, run wild here?
还轮到你在这儿撒野
I've dealt with countless men like you.
老娘都不知收拾多少个了
Send him back to the Wu's Mansion
送回吴府
and hand him over to Mrs. Wu!
交到吴夫人手上
Yes.
是
Let go!
放开
Who do you think you are?
你以为你们是谁啊
Let go! Let go of me!
放开 放开
Do you know who I am?
你知道我是谁吗
Bitch!
贱人
Are you alright?
你没事吧
Here you are, Mr. Qi.
齐公子 给
Master, what should we do with him?
主子 如何处置他
Do as Manager Yu said.
就按俞掌柜所说
Send him back to Mrs. Wu at the Wu's Mansion.
交还吴府吴夫人手上
Remember, send him back alive.
记得 要活着的
Don't cause trouble for Manager Yu.
别给俞掌柜找麻烦
-Yes! -Understood.
是 是
Manager Yu, you look pale.
俞掌柜脸色不太好
Were you frightened just now?
是刚才被吓到了吗
I'm fine.
没事
Thank you for saving me, Mr. Qi.
多谢齐公子出手相救
Farewell.
告辞
Manager, are you okay?
掌柜的 你没事吧
He behaves a bit like that guy,
行为有几分像
but there's no scar on his face.
但是脸上也没有疤
And the voice is different, too.
声音也不是这样子
Don't scare yourself.
别自己吓自己了
Why would he come to Lin'an?
他怎么会来林安呢
Who?
谁呀
Nothing.
没事
[Permeating fragrance]
这些点心都是给你准备的
My sister can really eat as well.
我阿姐也可能吃了
She eats enough for 3 meals in one sitting,
一顿饭能吃三顿饭
with her rice bowl as big as a soup tureen.
饭碗有汤砵那么大
Your sister is impressive!
你阿姐可真厉害
Have you ever seen a pig slaughter?
你见过杀猪吗
No.
没有
My sister can knock a pig out
我阿姐一巴掌
with one single slap.
就能把一个猪啰啰拍晕
Really?
真的
I've never seen anyone
我从来没见过
as formidable as your sister.
你阿姐这么厉害的人
Fuling, come over and help!
茯苓 赶紧过来帮忙了
I'm going out for a bit.
我先出去一趟
I'll be right back.
马上回来
Thief!
小偷
I... I'm not a thief.
我 我不是小偷
I don't care who you are.
我管你是谁
You are stealing food.
就是在偷吃
I'm going to tell my sister and the Fairy Sister.
我要告诉阿姐和仙女姐姐
Don't!
别
Changyu, someone is stealing food!
阿姐 有人来偷吃
Don't, please don't!
别 别
It's all because you're stealing food!
谁让你偷吃的
This is my home.
这是我家
My mother owns this restaurant.
我娘是这家酒楼的老板
Why can't I eat it?
我凭什么不能吃
You are the Fairy Sister's son?
你是仙女姐姐的儿子
What's your name? How old are you?
你叫什么名字 今年几岁
I'm Yu Bao'er. I'm 6.
我叫俞宝儿 今年六岁
What about you?
你呢
Try this piece.
你尝尝这一块
Just this piece is enough for me.
我吃这一块就可以了
Mother doesn't let me eat too much.
阿娘不让我多吃
She says too many sweets cause cavities.
说多吃甜食会长蛀牙的
What are cavities?
蛀牙是什么
They're like...
就是
Little worms will eat your teeth.
牙齿会被小虫子吃掉
It hurts so much.
很痛很痛
Worms will grow?
会长虫啊
Like cabbage worms or rice weevils?
是菜青虫那样 还是米虫那样
I don't know, either.
我也不知道
I've never had them.
我没长过
Then we'd better not eat anymore.
那还是别吃了吧
How about we go play outside together?
那咱俩要不一起出去玩
Mother says I have a special fate,
阿娘说我命格特殊
and I should avoid seeing too many people.
让我少见点人
Only then...
才
Only then can I stay safe.
才能保平安
Then let's play hide-and-seek.
那咱们就玩个躲猫猫
You can't take this.
不能拿这个
-Kids... -Go away.
这孩子 快走 快走
-Sorry. -I'm sorry.
对不起 对不起
Bao'er?
宝儿
Why are you here?
你怎么在这儿
-This way. -Let's go.
这边 快走快走
Your mother told you not to run around!
你娘不让你乱跑
You two. Don't touch it.
你们两个 别动
It doesn't matter.
有什么关系啊
-Just a moment. -OK, I'll go back later.
就一会 那一会我就回去
Where did you come from, brats?
哪儿来的小屁孩
You spoiled my mood. Get out.
坏我的好事 快出去
You're still running here?
还跑
Run!
快跑
You brats, how dare you ruin my day?
小屁孩 竟然敢坏我好事
Get lost!
滚一边去
Changning?
宁娘
She's not here.
不在这儿
I'll go in and light the lamps for you two first.
我先进去给您二位把灯点上
No need to light the lamps in this room.
这个房间不用点灯
Arrange the wine and dishes the same as on our first day here.
酒和菜按来时的一样安排
Got it.
好嘞
Keep this in mind.
记着
No matter when or where,
无论何时何地
never make decisions on my behalf,
都不要替孤做决定
even if we kill the wrong person.
即便是杀错了人
Do you understand?
听明白了吗
Yes.
是
I'm so sleepy.
我好眼困
Shh. Be quiet.
嘘 别吵
How is the investigation going?
那件事情查得怎么样了
I've asked around.
属下多方打探
Based on the time she arrived in Lin'an,
按着她来林安的年月推算
the child was very likely conceived in the Prince's Mansion.
那孩子极有可能是在王府怀的
To confirm her identity with absolute certainty,
若要十成十地确认身份
we need the Nanny to come to Lin'an to verify it in person.
还得嬷嬷亲自来林安验断
Then go arrange it now.
那还不赶紧去
I'll get on it right away.
属下这就去办
Who's there?
谁
Sold out so early?
这么早卖光啦
All sold out for today.
今日卖完了
Please come again tomorrow.
明日再来吧
Okay.
好
Make way.
让开
Mr. Li, where are these soldiers from?
李叔 这些官兵哪儿来的
Advisor Guo, who freeloaded here yesterday, said
昨天来吃白食的郭师爷说
the front lines are in trouble, so they're requisitioning grain again.
前线吃紧 又要征粮什么的
Looks like
看样子
these soldiers are here for the grain.
这些都是来征粮的兵
Wei Xuan's bound to be defeated.
魏宣败是迟早的事
I just didn't expect that he couldn't even hold on until the New Year.
没想到竟挨不到过年
I also heard
我还听说
that in Chongzhou, in order to collect grain,
崇州那边为了征粮
they drove farmers to their deaths.
逼死了农人
They all say Mr. He in our Jizhou is
都说咱们霁州的贺老爷
a just and upright official.
是青天大老爷
I hope he won't be like those in Chongzhou,
可千万别像崇州一样
just to collect grain,
为了征粮
driving the common people to their deaths.
把百姓往死里逼呀
It all depends on how the Jizhou Government will handle it.
就看这霁州府的作为了
What is this for?
这是做什么
It's yours.
你的
I don't need it. You keep it.
我不用 你收着吧
No.
不行
Half for each of us.
一人一半
You wrote hundreds of paper packets.
你写了几百张纸封呢
I might lose it if I carry it.
这放我身上容易丢
You keep it for me.
你替我收着吧
Fine. I'll keep it for you.
行吧 我替你收着
Okay.
好
Have you seen Changning?
你们有看见宁娘吗
She's missing.
她不见了
Those goddamn bandits are after us again?
那些天杀的又来了
-Bao'er! -Changning!
宝儿 宁娘
Bao'er!
宝儿
Who is Bao'er?
宝儿是谁啊
My son.
我儿子
Fuling!
茯苓
Manager, Bao'er isn't in the secret room.
掌柜的 宝儿不在密室里面
Changning was just here.
宁娘刚刚还在这儿的
I went out for a bit,
我出去一阵子的工夫
and she's gone.
她就不见了
Qi...
姓齐的
It must be him.
一定是那个姓齐的
Who is Qi?
姓齐的是谁
That man comes every day.
那人每日都来
Every time I see him,
每次一见到他
I get goosebumps.
我就起一身鸡皮疙瘩
He must be the one who took Bao'er away!
一定是他抓走了宝儿
Let's split up and search.
分头找
Okay.
好
Has that guest surnamed Qi left?
那姓齐的走了吗
I-I don't know.
小 小的不知
Manager, please calm down.
掌柜的 您冷静点
Where is that guy surnamed Qi?
那个姓齐的呢
He just left not long ago.
刚刚走没多久
Did he have anyone with him when he left?
他走时可有带着什么人
He left in a hurry.
他急匆匆地就离开了
I didn't notice
带没带人
whether he had anyone with him.
小的没注意
-Manager!
掌柜的
Calm down, please!
冷静点
Manager, are you alright?
掌柜的 没事吧
How is your hand?
手怎么样
Let me see.
我看看
I'll get on it right away.
属下这就去办
Who's there?
谁
Sir, it's me.
客官 是我
Sorry, sir.
客官 不好意思
I accidentally knocked over the lampstand just now.
刚才不小心把灯台打倒了
Did I disturb you?
没打扰您吧
Give it to me.
给我吧
You can go now.
这没你事儿了
Enjoy your meal.
您慢用
How have I taught you?
我平日是怎么教你的
I... I dare not forget, Mother.
不 不敢忘 阿娘
I was just...
我只是
Just what?
只是什么
Just playing around?
只是贪玩
Do you just let everything
我平日跟你说的话
I usually tell you go in one ear and out the other?
都当成耳旁风了吗
Why won't you listen?
为什么不听话
Why are you so playful?
为什么要贪玩
Qianqian, your hand is hurt.
浅姐 你手伤了
Why don't you go apply some medicine?
要不去上些药吧
Fairy Sister, please don't be mad.
仙女姐姐别生气
It's my fault. I fell asleep.
都怪我睡着了
Bao'er was just keeping me company.
宝儿也是为了陪着我
I won't blame you.
姐姐不怪你
Can I come play with Bao'er again in the future?
那我以后还能来找宝儿玩吗
Get up now. The ground is cold.
快起来吧 地上凉
Mother.
娘
Qianqian is usually so nice to everyone.
浅姐平日对谁都客客气气的
But why does she treat her own son like an enemy?
怎么对自己儿子跟个仇人一样
Her reaction today was
她今天的反应
indeed more fearful than yours.
确实比你还害怕一些
I'm going back to check on her.
我回去再看看她
Even close friends have their secrets.
即便是至交亦有各自隐衷
She will tell you when she wants to.
她想说的时候自然会和你说的
I wonder what Qianqian has been through.
也不知道浅姐到底经历了什么
Changyu, I'm sleepy.
姐 我困了
She's sleepy.
她困了
Come on, Changning.
来 宁娘
Hold onto me.
抱着我啊
[Peace at the border]
大胤一京十七府
the Northwest comprises 4 of them.
西北占四府
Jinzhou is barren, and Chongzhou has rebelled.
瑾州贫瘠 崇州已反
That leaves only 2 prefectures, Jizhou and Yanzhou.
只剩下霁 焉州两府
Yanzhou is
焉州
a garrison post.
乃屯兵之地
The Imperial Court strictly forbids hoarding grain or farming there.
朝廷严禁囤粮种地
That means right now in the Northwest,
也就是说现在西北
only our Jizhou prefecture can supply grain.
只有我们霁州一府可以供粮
Wei Xuan
那魏宣
clearly thinks the fire of war in Chongzhou is
分明是嫌崇州战场的火
not raging enough.
烧得还不够大
Wei Xuan sent troops to requisition grain by force.
魏宣派了军队强行征粮
The soldiers even took the seeds farmers kept.
农人留的谷种又被官兵夺了去
Forget about spring planting of the common people.
百姓别说明年春种
It'll already be a blessing for them to just survive the harsh winter.
严冬不饿死便算好的
Doing this is
这么做
like digging our own grave!
就同于自绝啊
Why couldn't we collect enough grain?
为何收不上来粮食
I've had it investigated.
属下已命人查过
A month ago,
一个月前
a group of merchants from out of town
一批外来的商人
bought up grain everywhere at high prices.
四处高价回收粮食
The people only kept seeds and coarse grain for themselves,
百姓只留了谷种和自家吃的粗粮
and sold all the rest.
其余的全都卖了
Buying grain in wartime.
临阵收粮
Go investigate these merchants from out of town.
去查一下这批外来的商人
-Yes, General.
属下领命
Your Lordship, I've figured it out.
侯爷 查清楚了
The one who bought grain in the city is
城中收粮之人
the manager of Lin'an Rice Shop,
是林安米行的掌柜
named Zhao Xun.
叫赵询
He united grain merchants from many places
他联合多地粮商
to buy grain at high prices in Yanzhou and Jizhou,
在焉州 霁州高价收粮
totaling nearly 200,000 piculs.
近二十万石
Zhao Xun?
赵询
Has he been closely interacting with someone recently?
最近他可与何人过从甚密
Yes, someone who claimed to be a rice merchant from the Capital,
有 说是京城来的米商
surnamed Qi.
姓齐
Qi?
齐
Mr. Qi,
齐公子
our manager hasn't recovered from her cold yet.
我们掌柜的感染风寒未愈
She has been resting behind closed doors
一直在闭门养病
and really can't see anyone.
实在是不便见人
Hope you can understand it, sir.
还请公子见谅
If it's a cold,
既是风寒
why didn't she accept
为何不收
the medicine I had a famous doctor prescribe for her?
我找名医为她配制的汤药
She didn't even accept the fox-fur coat.
连狐裘也不收
Is it not warm enough for her?
是不够她驱寒吗
Or is it that
还是说
your manager is avoiding me on purpose?
你们掌柜在故意躲我
No way.
哪里
Our manager doesn't mean to slight you.
我们掌柜的不是有意怠慢
She is just seriously ill.
实在是病情严重
How serious?
有多严重
She's not dead yet, is she?
不是还没死吗
Tell her,
你告诉她
I always get to see the person I want to see.
我要见到的人 就必须要见到
So it's you, Mr. Qi! Welcome.
原来是齐公子来啦
Go serve the dishes. The best ones.
快去上菜 上好菜
Yes.
是
Serve the most expensive ones.
上最贵的
It seems you're fine.
看来你没事
It's just a cold.
风寒而已
Nothing serious.
并无大碍
Besides, the physician said it's more important to keep inner peace.
而且大夫说养心更重要
Don't get angry or sad,
别生气 别难过
and avoid looking at disgusting things.
恶心的东西少看
That helps with recovery.
更有利于恢复
Don't move.
别动
Men and women aren't supposed to get intimate.
男女授受不亲
Please show some respect, Mr. Qi.
还希望齐公子自重
I said, don't move.
我说别动
Your pulse was slow just now.
方才脉缓
It's indeed like a chill.
确像风寒
But now it has quickened a lot.
这会儿倒快了很多
This medicine is exactly what you need.
这些药正适合你
Thank you, Mr. Qi.
多谢齐公子
Manager Yu, you seem to dislike me so much.
俞掌柜似乎很讨厌我
What are you talking about?
您这话说的
It's not that I dislike you.
哪有什么讨厌不讨厌的
It's just that I haven't recovered from my cold,
只是我这风寒未愈
and I'm afraid I'll spoil your mood
怕耽误了齐公子
for enjoying the delicacies.
品尝美味佳肴的心情
I'll take my leave then.
那我先告辞啦
Where are you going?
去哪儿
None of your business.
关你屁事
I wanted you to take the medicine
我让你用药
for your own good.
是为了你好
There are plenty of men who care about me.
关心我的男人多了去了
Go wait in line.
排队去吧
Who are they?
谁
Let go.
你放开
What are you doing?
你干什么
Mr. Qi's concern for Manager Yu is
齐公子对俞掌柜的一番关切心意
truly a grand gesture.
真的是大手笔
He actually booked the entire Yixiang Restaurant.
竟然包了这溢香楼
Manager Yu,
俞掌柜
now you can have a good rest.
这回可以好生休息了
You booked my Yixiang Restaurant?
你包了我的溢香楼
Manager Zhao just said
刚刚赵掌柜说
he'd offer 100 taels a day
要以每日百两的价格
to book the Yixiang Restaurant for 10 days.
包下溢香楼十日
Ten days.
十日
I'm booking everything
这溢香楼里的一切
in the Yixiang Restaurant.
我包了
Only 100 taels a day?
每日才一百两
Did you not bring enough money?
你是不是没带够银子啊
At least 1,000 taels a day.
最起码一日一千两
Not a wen less.
少一文免谈
Do you have that much?
有吗
Just this little?
就这么点啊
That's strange.
奇怪了
The Manager didn't notify us.
这掌柜的也没通知我们啊
-Excuse me. -The Restaurant is closed to reorganize.
借过一下 溢香楼歇业重整
We appreciate your understanding.
望诸位客官见谅
Why is it closed all of a sudden?
为何忽然会歇业呀
Where is Manager Yu?
俞掌柜人呢
We also came to work early this morning
我们也是一早来上工
and just found out.
才知道这个消息的
We haven't seen Manager Yu.
没见着俞掌柜
This is weird.
奇了怪了
Madam Man, Mr. Li.
满婆 李叔
Why is the Yixiang Restaurant closed?
溢香楼怎么关了
Mr. Qi booked the whole place.
被那姓齐的公子包了场
He sent us back to rest for a few days,
打发我们回去休息几日
saying he doesn't need us to serve.
说不用我们伺候
It's weird, though.
说也奇怪
Even the doors are all locked.
门头都锁上了
In all my years at the Yixiang Restaurant,
我在溢香楼这几年
I've never seen this happen before.
还从未遇到这样的事
Indeed.
是啊
Where is Qianqian?
那浅姐呢
She was sick yesterday,
她昨天就病着
so she must be inside now.
那肯定在里头啊
Yes.
对啊
I'll go take a look.
我去瞧瞧
The doors are locked.
这门都锁了
You're not actually thinking of flying...
您该不会是想飞
She actually flew over.
真飞过去了
Qianqian!
浅姐
-Qianqian! -Don't come over!
浅姐 不要过来
Help!
救命
Don't come over. Stay back.
不要过来 不要过来
-Qianqian. -No...
浅姐 不要
No.
不要
-No! -Qianqian.
我不要 浅姐
Get lost!
滚开
-Go away!
浅姐 走开
No!
不要
Changyu...
长玉
It's okay.
没事了
What's wrong?
你怎么了
What dream did you have
做什么梦了
to scare you so much?
吓成这样
I dreamed of a madman.
我梦到一个疯子了
Go away!
滚开
A masked madman.
带面具的疯子
Here you are.
来
Madam Man said the Yixiang Restaurant was
满婆说溢香楼
booked by Mr. Qi.
被一位姓齐的公子包了
What's going on?
怎么回事啊
No.
没有
I didn't dare take on this business.
这生意我可不敢做
Why?
怎么了
I deliberately asked for 1,000 taels,
我故意开价一千两
but he still agreed.
这样他都答应
The more I thought about it, the more scared I got.
越想我越害怕
So I just closed up the restaurant to avoid him.
干脆关门躲一躲他
Is it possible
有没有一种可能
that he just likes you?
只是这个人他喜欢你
I don't know.
我也不知道
I just feel like
总感觉这件事情
it's not that simple.
没有这么简单
How about I tie him up in a sack,
要不我用麻袋把他绑了
beat him up,
揍他一顿
and ask what he wants?
问问他口风
Beating people up isn't a long-term solution.
你揍人一顿也不是长久之计啊
Isn't Butcher Guo the best example?
那郭屠户不就是最好的例子吗
Besides, booking a restaurant isn't illegal.
而且人家包场吃饭又没犯法
That makes sense.
有道理
Why is this clingy guy so annoying?
这狗皮膏药怎么这么烦啊
I've seen enough of this domineering, big-spending act.
这一掷千金的霸道戏码我看多了
If he really just likes me,
若他真的只是喜欢我
and I want him to give up completely,
要想让他彻底死心
I must sever his emotional attachment.
得从感情上断了他的念想
I have to let him know
得让他知道
that I already have a husband,
我已有夫婿
so he doesn't stand a chance.
他再无可乘之机
But you don't have a husband.
可你没有啊
You do.
你有啊
I do, but you don't.
我有你没有啊